I had this experience of I am one with
everything and everything is good. It
was like getting hooked on heroin. I was
like whatever the [laughter] that is,
I'm obsessed.
>> I'm excited to have you here, Joe.
Welcome to the podcast. I don't know if
you know kind of what this podcast is
all about, but basically the people who
listen to this podcast are very much
like me and Sam. We're business junkies.
We're entrepreneurs. were sort of
perpetually always starting things but
also students of the game always trying
to learn. You've done many things. You
started your life story in 10 seconds
was kind of like a kind of punk rock kid
to discovering an entire area of wisdom
to go work in. You've been in the
business world as a VC and now you coach
some of the highest level players of the
game. You are one of the coaches to some
of the top uh CEOs and entrepreneurs in
the game including Sam Alman and some
other friends that we we we were talking
about before we started. And so we're
really excited to have you here.
>> Are you able to name drop at all? Can we
give you like 10 seconds just to brag?
>> The names that I can drop are the ones
that are on the website. I find that
it's better if you all name drop for me
than me name.
>> We've seen Mark Pinkis, we've seen
Samuel Alman, we've seen Eric Torberg,
Ev Williams, I think
>> Ev is a good one. Yeah. Um Stacy Philpot
Brown, she was head of Google India and
ran Task Rabbit. Is your specialty like
type A high achievers that just need a
little bit of help? Like how do you
summarize the um you're starting here
and you end up here?
>> Uh no, I I I really like to have a
variety of people, you know, like all
sorts of people. The only thing that I
think all of all the people that I work
with have in common is they're
ambitious. Only some of them are
maximalists, but they're all super
ambitious.
>> What's a maximalist?
>> I don't even know what that is. Yeah.
What's maximalist? Maximalist is someone
who's like, I want it all right now and
I can get it all right now. I would put
like Sam Alman in the maximalist
category. Any limitation that a normal
person would see, they're just like,
"No, we can figure out how to do both."
>> Is that achievable?
>> No, I don't think it's achievable
entirely, but I think that much more is
achievable if you think that way. Right.
So, the limitation like limiting beliefs
are like hold us back dramatically. Let
me ask you a question about limiting
beliefs. I had never heard this phrase
till I went to a Tony Robbins event and
then he started explaining it and I
started now then I started seeing it
everywhere in myself and my my family
members different people where people we
tell ourselves these stories. Can you
can you talk a little bit about this
because I think it's pretty universal.
The yeah the idea of a limiting belief
outwardly is just any thought process
that you have holding you back. And so
I'll give you one that probably
everybody has experienced. they have
some sort of transformation, something
happens, and then they ask themselves,
"Will it last?" That's a great limiting
belief.
>> Cuz all that really is is just a whole
bunch of anxiety presenting itself as a
thought process for you to believe. And
in instead of saying like, "Oh, every
learning that I've ever had es and
flows, like I've totally learned stuff
and then I've forgotten it and then I
relearn it." Or, "I've been able to make
that shot in golf and then I can't make
it." But then I learn to make it over
time that there's this natural
pendulation of learning that occurs. And
so the es and flows are actually good
because that is what learning is.
Instead, it's oh, I might lose this
thing. And then they have a moment where
they've lost this moment of
transformation and then they go, "Oh,
I've lost it, which is a second limiting
belief." So that would be like a very
common limiting belief that people have.
Or they're like they're on a diet and
they're like, "Will I be able to
maintain the diet?" and then they have
that one piece of chocolate cake and
they're like, "Oh, well, I I couldn't
maintain the diet,
>> right?"
>> As if they couldn't like just have the
piece of chocolate cake and then go back
to the diet.
>> Well, you don't need to make it
personal, Joe. I don't appreciate
[laughter] that.
>> Sam, when when we say limiting belief,
does one pop into your head.
>> Um, yeah. Like for example, you have to
grind really hard um and do tons of
stuff that you don't like in order to
get to the end result, which in this
case, let's say selling a company or
making a lot of money
>> and you must suffer and suffer and
suffer and once you achieve whatever the
end goal is, you will be at a place
where you are new and happy. [laughter]
>> That's a great one.
>> Hypothetically, yeah, you know, I've
heard that two.
>> Yeah. Asking for a friend. Yeah. There
there's
two beliefs in there. The first one is
that you have to suffer to achieve what
you want to achieve or that you have to
grind to achieve what you want to
achieve. So I have a client who I can't
mention their name and probably one of
the most successful VCs ever has been
involved in some of the biggest
companies and most of their investments
have been in big companies. I think they
work like three or four hours a week and
they had like a grind period of a couple
of days, I mean a couple of years kind
of in their 20s, but they just just
don't work really hard. And I can name
another 10 people who have been able to
be incredibly successful without
grinding like that. They've just been
able to be in the right place at the
right time. And then the secondary piece
of that grind is
>> if you want to hit your goals, you need
a system. And so I worked with HubSpot
to put together a step-by-step process
showing you how I use ChatGpt as a life
coach. So I uploaded my personal
finances, my net worth, my goals, and
the output is that I have this GPT that
I can ask questions that I'm having
issues with in my life, like how should
I respond to this email, what's the
right decision, things like that. And
it's literally changed my life. And so
if you want that, it's free. We will
send you everything you need to know to
set this up in just about 20 minutes.
and I'll show you how I use it. So,
check it out. The link is below in the
description. Back to the episode.
>> Here's something that I've never seen.
I've never seen a venture company or a
startup fail because of lack of effort.
Everybody is like anybody who's got a
startup in Silicon Valley anyways, they
are efforting all the time and yet a
tremendous amount of them fail. But the
idea is if I work harder, I'll succeed.
But obviously that's not true.
So then the question is like what is the
most important thing that you're doing?
And it's usually the relationships you
hold and the decisions that you make.
>> How do you teach people how to flip
that? Because like for example, if I go
to the news all day, I see like these
big exits or these big funding rounds
and you constantly particularly right
now have this feeling of I'm being left
behind because everything's changing so
fast. And you just said it's the
relationships. So that's one of these
things where you read a book like how to
win friends and influence people and
you're like duh that's obvious and it
almost becomes a reminder and yet I'm
like but how do you tactically make that
switch where you say enjoy the
relationships not seeking the outcome?
>> Yeah. So if you're going to make any
transformation effectively in your
system you have basically three levels
that you need to address it at. The
first level is the the level of the mind
and this is what we're usually pretty
good at. meaning most people know that
they should work out, but it doesn't
mean that they work out. Most people
know they shouldn't be dicks to the
people who they need to run their
business, but not everybody is. So,
intellectually understanding that's
actually usually the easiest part for
Americans is to actually get that to gro
that. And then there's the emotional
level, the mamillian level of the brain.
So, the prefrontal cortex is the
thinking level of the brain. It's very
human. And the mamleian level I would
like call it the heart. I call it the
emotional. And so a lot of the times if
we're trying to make transformation, we
have to look at what's emotionally
needed to make that transformation
happen. And then there's the part of our
system that's more of the reptilian.
It's the nervous system. And is that
nervous? Can we address the nervous
system? So if you want to make real
transformation, you have to address all
three levels of the the system. Can you
walk through an example of that? So,
like what's the transformation and then
because you know you you had me at the
head, you sort of lost me at the heart
and then by the time we got to the
nervous system I I I I didn't know what
to do. I don't know. I don't know how to
I don't have the the instruction manual
for that one. So, let's take an example
and walk through.
>> So, let's do an example that probably
touches most of the entrepreneurs that
listen to this. Self-reliance. So, the
self-reliance pattern is basically a
pattern that somewhere when you were
young, you were taught that you had to
fend for yourself. you and 90% of the
time it meant you had to fend for other
people. You had to take care of other
people. Maybe that's because your
parents were super critical or maybe
it's because you had an alcoholic father
and you needed to take care of that
father or you had a depressed mother.
But somewhere you learned, hey, no one's
going to be there to take care of me. I
got to take care of myself. My needs
aren't going to be met otherwise. And
then the outcome of that is that those
people have a hard time asking for help.
Typically, they have a hard time owning
what they want, being able to just say,
"This is clearly what I want." They
usually have an authority problem which
means they neither want to be the
authority because they don't trust they
because they don't trust the authority
of their childhood. They don't want they
don't fully step into their own
authority and they kind of rebel against
other authorities. So they have like
this mixed relationship with authority
typically and then they have a very hard
time announcing that they're hurt. Like
it's the last move that they'll make is
to say, "Hey, I'm hurt." Right? And so
that's the pattern that comes out of
self-reliance. So now how would you
address it? The first way is to talk
about like the way I just talked about
it. I saw both of you and probably most
of the people in the audience click and
oh I never is that's all related really
like to be able to tie that together to
show that this is a pattern that came
from your childhood. It isn't particular
reality and so that kind of like creates
a little space for a different action,
different movement, but oftent times
just seeing it's not going to really
deal with it. So then there's the
emotional level. The emotional level is
two things, right? Typically, but there
can be others, but typically there's an
emotion of helplessness that I refuse to
feel. I'm not going to feel
helplessness. I will go and like storm
the gates of hell. I will grind forever
over the idea of feeling helpless,
>> dude. I'll walk into the grocery store
and not see what I want and refuse to
ask the counter guy where the thing is.
So, trust me, I'm
>> Exactly.
>> I'll leave. We're not We're not eating
[laughter] that tonight.
>> Exactly. Exactly. So, so there's this
feeling of helplessness that those
people will absolutely not feel because
as a kid if you felt that helplessness,
if you're like, "Holy there's
nobody here taking care of me." It's
like death and destruction. So, you
don't do that. And so, this feeling of
helplessness never got to be felt as a
kid. And so emotionally it means you
have to learn how to feel the
helplessness and and how to actually
look forward to and enjoy the
helplessness which sounds radical and
impossible
but the way that this works is what what
I will call the golden algorithm what we
call the golden algorithm. So the
emotion that you're trying to avoid is
the emotion you're inviting in the exact
way that you're trying to avoid it.
So, you don't want to feel helpless in
the grocery store, so you don't ask for
help, which means you walk away without
the thing in the grocery store. Or you
don't want to feel helpless about your
business not doing well, so you grind,
which keeps you more burnt out, making
less good decisions,
destroys your relationship, so you feel
more helpless. So the action that you're
taking to not feel the thing is actually
what perpetuates the thing. In this
case, helplessness. So learning how to
say, "Oh, I'm helpless. I know how to
experience that feeling. I know how to
actually go, "Oh, this is just an
emotional thing that's moving through
me, and I don't have to be ruled by it.
It It's not my boss anymore." Cuz if
you're all your decisions are based on
not feeling helpless, it means there are
certain risks you're not going to take.
It means you're not going to rely on
other people that you need to to scale
the business etc etc etc right so that
would be the emotional
>> is is the right way to think about it
like um it's a counter to the idea of
what you seek you know what you seek you
shall find it's almost like what you
avoid you shall experience
>> yeah yeah the self Yeah exactly
>> so then but if we were going to play on
like the phrase that what Sean just said
or whatever um I think you said whatever
emotion you try to avoid you end up
inviting into your So then what's the
opposite? What's the inverse of that?
What's like the sentence that um is the
solution?
>> Fall in love with the emotions you're
avoiding.
>> Like think about it this way. It's just
like working out. You want to work out,
you're going to have to like lean into
the burn. And eventually you're like, I
like working out. I like that burn. Is
the same thing for emotions.
>> And then on like a day-to-day basis,
let's just say that we are doing the
hard work or like this has to suck in
order to get a good result.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Do you tell what do you tell yourself
every day for the next 2 years? Like are
there like common inner thoughts that
you find to be productive for this
emotional state?
>> So that answer is part of the pattern
you're trying to interrupt. What do I do
every day? One, every day. Two, what do
I do? Those are the two things that make
you grind. It's up to me. I got to do
it. There's no grace. There's no
surrender. There's no letting other
people help me. and I got to do it every
day.
>> What's the thing that I do that I can
control that I can grind at that will
fix my grind? So, if you're really
taking a look at it yet, it's it's
actually not it doesn't work like that
at all. And and the cool thing is it it
can often just be I've literally seen
the moment that somebody fully
understands the beauty of the emotion.
Oh, I can't wait to feel helpless
because when I feel helpless, what I
know is that I am
not delegating well. What I know is that
I'm not letting other people help me.
What I know is that my decision-m is
constrained by a false limitation. So,
I'm so stoked that I'm feeling it
because I have those three signals now.
And I'm going to go take action on those
three things because I know that signal
in my system. And as soon as they get
that, they don't there's no more effort
required.
>> Is the right way to think of these
feelings as like a messenger kind of the
way you're describing it. If you if you
reframe them as a messenger or a signal,
then it's not something to you know, you
don't shoot the messenger, you don't
avoid the messenger, you take the
message and then you you you use it and
move through it. Is that the right way
to think about this or is that a
>> It's kind of h say half of it. The other
half is to see that the that the
emotional thing that's happening is
let's say like it's a tube of energy,
right? And so like a a a hose with water
running through it. And if it runs
clear, meaning it's not that hose isn't
kinkedked, then life is good. If it
kinks in one way or another, then
there's all sorts of problems that
happen. So let's take anger as an
example. So you have anger moving
through
your system and you kink it one way and
it's like this nice dress.
And you kink it another way and it's
like this. I'm not angry. I just need
you to do the thing. I'm not angry. And
you kink it another way and it's like
this. You motherucker, you.
But if you uncink it, if you actually
let that emotion go through, which means
you're not having resistance or shame,
you don't think that you're bad for
having it, then anger looks like Martin
Luther King or Gandhi. It's
determination and clarity. And when you
see CEOs do this where they go, "Oh,
right. I'm constantly pissed because I
constantly feel like I'm alone in it and
I constantly feel like no one's got my
back." Even though I have 20,000 people
showing up to work every day and none of
them have ever thought, "Boy, I really
hope the CEO is upset with me today."
Or, "Boy, I hope that the work I did
doesn't please the CEO." So, you got
20,000 people trying to please a CEO who
feels all alone in it. And so they
they're getting angry. And when they
realize, oh wait, if I don't resist
this, if I just listen to it, then
there's actually some wisdom here. And
if there's the and then they start
listening to it without that shame,
without that kink and all of a sudden
they're like, "Oh, that means I have a
boundary. It means that's something
inefficient is happening in the company
and I need to go pay attention there."
>> You you seem very into words and I and I
buy into that. I think you like use
these phrases and then it kind of like
shapes the way you think. And you called
out some of the words that I use and
that that's pretty helpful. But are
there other like on the emotional level
words or phrases that you have found
that if you change or shift or tell
yourself consistently that they seem to
have um positive impacts on type A
people?
>> Yeah, absolutely. There are. However,
the the the awareness is more important
than the words.
So let let's let's take for instance a
common thing that is is effective is you
know positive affirmations or uh you
know visualizing things going right. I'm
going to go into a meeting and I'm going
to visualize things going right. So you
can do that and there's a certain amount
of effectiveness. It's even more
effective if you visualize it going
right and you feel the emotions of it
going right. It's even more effective if
you visualize it going right in the
present instead of in the future. So you
can actually feel what it's happening
right now. So all of those things that's
like that's really effective. But if you
really have the awareness of what's
behind that,
then it's going to be a lot more
powerful. And so what's actually
happening say with the positive
reinforcement is that you're changing
your identity. You're saying, "Okay, I'm
no longer this person. I'm going to
visualize myself as this person and
that's going to change my identity.
And if you're really looking at identity
shift and being comfortable with
identity shift then you also have to
visualize the negative outcomes so that
you don't get scared of them. The
samurai use this the
I mean so many traditions use this which
is visualizing their own death and they
Tibetan book of living and dying samurai
and then also what was it is like the
Marcus Aurelius. Yeah, there's a great
stoic book, Stoicism book, where you
like close your eyes for five minutes
and you assume everyone's dead, your
kids have cancer, the worst things on
earth. You open up your eyes and you
say, "None of that is true. How grateful
am I?"
>> Yeah.
>> Right. So, so the if you visualize this
and you actually feel the destruction
that you're trying to avoid,
then you've already lived it. So, you
don't have to be scared of it anymore.
So, I I'll give you an example of this
with my with my wife. So, we've been
married 27 years. I've been married to
at least three women in that 27 years.
She's like, she's changed dramatically.
I've changed dramatically. And so, we
come to points in our relationship where
it's not working for us. And what our
what our path is is that we both grieve
the relationship. It's over. We're
getting a divorce. We visualize the
divorce. It's horrible. we like have the
entire experience because once we've had
it, we don't have to be scared of it
anymore. And so when we show up, we act
as ourselves. We don't try to
accommodate. We don't walk on eggshells.
We don't we're like, "No, this is what I
want." And then we can actually have a
conversation how we can both be happy as
we are now, not trying to save the
marriage.
>> The the visualization thing is
interesting. Um, the inner game of
tennis talks a lot about that.
>> Great book. And I actually just listened
to um uh a talk by the coach of George
St. Pierre, who's one of the greatest
UFC fighters of all time. And they talk
about preparing fighters for the most
dangerous, scary sport there is. And he
was like, "We find the competitor's
walkout music. We wear our outfit, you
know, our we're like a dress rehearsal.
We listen to the music constantly." And
so we do that when we practice. And we
practice the walk out. We have the
bright lights. This way you are
visualizing this to the point of not
just visualizing but you hear it and
like he was even saying something about
the smell. They try to get use the same
glove so it smells the same. And this
way when you first when you're going
into this thing that's a life-changing
thing you have been there before because
you can sort of trick yourself into
thinking this is real and you are
prepared. It's the same thing like so I
don't know how many entrepreneurs I've
walked through that the visualization of
the death of their company. Everybody
gets laid off, you know, people go
broke. Same thing. It's the same thing.
You visualize the end of the company so
that you can stop acting from fear and
you can actually build the company that
you want to build and be the person that
you want to be.
>> Do you do that daily, monthly? Like how
often should someone practice that?
>> It's more until the fear is gone. And
it's not really how often, but it's how
you do it. So example would be like if
you do it and you actually deeply feel
the emotions of it then it's probably
you don't have to do it very many times
until the fear dissipates then that's
going to like it's how you do it is more
important than than than
repetition and reps and what is the how
you do it you you sit in a room turn the
lights off like walk me through what how
do you actually do this
>> I just sit down close my eyes and
visualize everything and anything that I
don't want to visualize, I slow way the
down and feel everything I don't want to
feel.
>> The the big trick is to feel the things
you don't want to feel. The reason that
that's the trick is because look, if I
said to you like most entrepreneurs, one
of the things that they get scared about
is being homeless. Who knows why, but it
is something that many entrepreneurs get
scared about. And if I said to you, hey,
you're going to be homeless, but you are
going to be happier, more content,
you're going to feel
Great. Like how the think of the best
time you've ever felt in your entire
life, it's going to be 10x that all the
time. If if you knew that to be true,
how scared are you to be homeless?
>> I want to be homeless.
>> Right. Exactly. So, what's actually
occurring
is that we're scared of an emotional
experience, not an actual experience.
And and and and it's neurologically this
is proven. So, if I was to take the
emotional center out of your brain, you
would have an IQ that is the same as it
is now, but you would have an incredibly
hard time making decisions and your
total life would fall apart. So, and you
can read a book about this. It's called
Deart's Error. It was written by a
neuroscientist in like 2012 or
something. And so, we've known this for
a long time. So basically, if I pull out
that emotional
um part of your brain, it's going to
take you like a half an hour to decide
what color pen to use. It's going to
take you an hour or two to decide where
to have lunch. So your whole life falls
apart cuz you can't make decisions. And
this was people who had brain damage or
like a stroke in a certain area that and
you oh your logical center is still
working and decisions are logical,
right?
>> Yes.
>> And it's like no, no, not not right. Not
even simple decisions are
>> the the only decisions that aren't
emotionally based are the decisions that
bypass the emotional center like a snake
coming at you
>> like you jump back without without it
going through that part of your brain.
>> What about the the nervous system bit
because that seems like the most
challenging. I've read The Body Keeps
the Score and I like intuitively know
that like trauma is a physical thing,
but like to put it on a really practical
level, you ever get like a slack or an
email from a co-orker that says, "Can we
talk?" And you're like, "They're
quitting.
>> I feel like you feel like you get
goosebumps and you like you feel
something."
>> Um, how do you how do you address this
at a neurological level?
>> Yeah. So, nervous system, that's like a
super tricky one. There's a lot of
things that you can do, but this is like
it's all very primal. And this is where
like repetition and do I do this every
day? This is where it really comes in
handy. So there's not like an
intellectual or emotional aha that can
change a nervous system just like that.
Occasionally like high doses of like
psilocybin or something I've seen change
nervous systems,
but it's very undependable. And so this
is actually where repetition matters in
the nervous system. So one of the like
the key principles is how do you allow
yourself to experience pleasure
more and more deeply because pleasure
means that we're not under attack. So
our nervous system thinks that we're
under attack when we're not and so it it
amps up. Now sometimes that occurs
because we have an abusive self-t talk
and so if there's if I had a if I was
your boss and I was like oh you you that
up you did that wrong like why are you
biting your nails why aren't you looking
at Joe while you're while you're
podcasting why are you taking notes
instead of being connected to your
co-host like if I was doing that
perpetually it would cause you stress
because you're perpetually under attack
but often we're doing that to ourselves
And so that's activating the nervous
system. So that is the intellectual
that's like how how the intellect and
the nervous system relate. But there's a
whole bunch of things that also happen
with the nervous system. I I'll use my
own example in this is my mom German
super rigid woman loved me dearly in her
capacity
but like if I was 5 minutes early I was
late and I would get in trouble you know
it was like that kind of a thing and
like things needed to be very perfect
and so there was a sense of obligation
and if I wasn't going to fulfill that
obligation I was going to be in trouble
and so my nervous system gets activated
when you know I'm a minute late for a
podcast though it's not going to affect
anything my nervous system is going to
get messed up so there's some nervous
system stuff that happens just like
through training and so one the the kind
of the overall background thought
process is how do I allow as much
pleasure as possible as to like to reset
my baseline but the second thing is to
really start to notice and be present
with for like one or two seconds those
moments when my nervous system is
activated or when your nervous system is
activated. So when that phone call comes
in and you're like, "Oh shit." You just
stop and you're like, "What is it like
to be me?" 2 seconds and then you go
ahead and do your thing. Like go ahead,
be anxious again. Like don't don't try
to control yourself because trying to
control your anxiety is just anxiety
producing, right? like it just it just
creates more of the same thing. It's
just being really really in touch with
what's going on. Like bringing awareness
into that moment is all that's really
necessary. But it's necessary to do it
over and over and over again to see
what's actually occurring in your system
and and what's really necessary. And
then pretty soon it unpacks what's going
on beneath your nervous system. Your
intellect starts to understand it. But
your intellect will never get it at
first. It it really requires lots of
just being with present for one or two
seconds when you notice that activation
occur. Hey, can I ask you about avoiding
conflict? Something that I I thought,
you know, I think I'm usually pretty
good at, but man, lately there's been a
situation where I'm just I can see
myself doing it. I can feel myself doing
it. I know I'm not supposed to be doing
it, but I'm doing it. By God, I'm doing
it. and uh you know I don't really have
a lot of language or kind of experience
or wisdom around this and I was really
hoping you could help me out with that.
So so can we talk about conflict and
avoiding conflict uh especially with
those who we're closest to where I think
it's maybe the hardest.
>> Yeah. So I think intellectually the the
the important thing to recognize about
conflict it is imagine you're working in
a factory
and somebody can tell you where the
machine is going to break or someone can
point to you this is where the machine's
broken this is where the machine's
broken
and you're like great thanks and you
ignore it. That's what avoiding conflict
is like because
conflict is the place where efficiency
can be gained whether it's in a marriage
or in a business or between business
partners.
So I I I'll give you um a a story about
this. So recently we had a facilitator
in our business and somebody who
probably wants to be a facilitator in
our business and the who felt like the
facilitator wasn't doing a good job and
wanted to give the facilitator feedback
and we have a very open culture where
everybody can give anybody feedback
and we could say you know you need to go
to their boss and then their boss will
have the conversation because we're
going to avoid the conflict and and
we're and as a as company deciding like
how does this feedback is this feedback
going to work? And what we realize is
that if this person gives feedback to
the facilitator and the facilitator gets
hurt, that's something that for the
facilitator to work on. And if this
person's doing it out of some sort of
like arrogance or um
uh narcissism, like I think I can do a
better job and the feedback is
then that needs to be addressed. But
either way, if he has arrogance and
narcissism, addressing that's going to
make our business better. If this
facilitator isn't doing a good job,
that's going to make our business
better. And so, every time that we're
avoiding conflict in a business, we're
looking at a place that we could
potentially make the system better and
we're not going to do it,
>> right? Yeah. You're avoiding progress,
not not conflict.
>> Exactly. Yeah. Thank you. Yeah.
>> Yeah. But that's what a lot of people
feel like. Like for example, I've talked
to like really big big shot tycoon types
and they'll be like, "I need to let go
of this person, but I'm too afraid of
the conversation."
>> And so, like you just said this on a on
an intellectual level,
>> totally I'm I'm on board. Totally agree.
Everything you're saying makes tons of
sense
>> and yet I'm still like but I don't have
the courage or I don't have the toolbox
or the language to do this effectively.
>> Yeah. So, let Yeah. Let's get into that.
that I think that the I I do want to say
one more thing intellectually too
because it's um that if I was if I go in
and monitor a company's health, I
literally just use two metrics. How
quickly do they have the hard
conversation
and how quickly do they resolve it? So
let's say you have a CEO who's a yeller.
I guarantee you that the a lot of hard
conversations aren't going to be had and
they're not resolving quickly. And let's
say you have a CEO who's conflict
avoidant. a lot of hard conversations
aren't going to be had and a lot of
things are going to be avoided. So, it
doesn't really matter what the actions
are of people. Just to think about those
two metrics as the health of an
organization is just a great way to go
in and very quickly see how healthy that
organization is. Okay. So, now how do
you do it? So, typically before we get
into how you do it, let's talk about the
resistance to it. So, the resistance is
usually I'm going to be abandoned, not
loved.
This is a waste of my time. I'm not
going to get anywhere anyway and it's
going to take so much energy I could use
the energy somewhere else. That's the
second reason that people choose not to
do it. And the third is I'm going to
destroy something that I care about.
Like I have the hard conversation, that
person leaves, and then the company's
going to collapse or then the sales
department's going to collapse or
whatever.
>> Is there a fourth one which is like I
don't even know if this is a problem
worth addressing. Maybe I should just
give it time. I feel like that's like a
a reason for one of the other excuses,
but I'm sure that there's moments where
that that's the case. And sometimes
that's there's actually some there's
some validity to that. Like I've given
them feedback. I'm going to wait a
couple weeks and see what happens
instead of like be on their ass every
day about the thing. I can see that
there would be some validity to it. And
so some of that speaks to the fact that
the person doesn't know how to make the
conflict productive reliably.
Like I have conflict and it just ends up
in a worse fight that just like doesn't
go the place that I want to go. So
typically if I'm talking about it, let's
just take one example cuz this gets a
little complex. If I'm taking just I
want to have a hard conversation with
somebody, what do I do? The first thing
that I'm going to do is I am going to
not solve the problem for them. So most
people in a hard conversation say, "Hey,
sales is off and what I need you to do
is make more phone calls and we're going
to monitor those through this set of
data." Right? That's incredibly
disempowering and that conversation
usually doesn't go very well. But if you
say instead, "Hey, sales are off. I need
a plan. please present it to me tomorrow
about how we're going to get sales back
on track. That's a far more powerful way
to do it because you're not you're not
disempowering the person and you're not
coming in and telling them what to do.
So letting them solve the problem for
you rather than you solve the problem
for them. you solving the problem for
them is self-reliance again and it's
what most CEOs do instead of let them
solve the problem for you which is far
more empowering to them and it makes
them feel like like they can't blame you
for it. So that's one of the like skills
that I would teach. The other one is I
would really try to understand their
situation before having the hard
conversation. So I would ask a lot of
open-ended questions. I would make sure
that they feel very heard and so I
understand what's going on. So, as a
CEO, I sit down and I'm like, I have an
idea of what's going on over here in
billing, but I don't I do not have the
full picture. If I have the full
picture, I should fire the person
because they're not doing a job good
enough where I don't have to pay
attention. So, the first thing I want to
do is really ask their context and
understand what's actually going on with
them and see like if they're even happy
with the job that they're doing or
what's going on. Actually, another thing
I would do is I would actually be very
vulnerable about where I am with it. So,
I would say something like, "Wow, I feel
like um we've lost trust." Like I I'm I
notice that like I'm not trusting that
this is going to get done and so I'm not
having confidence around this and that
sucks for me and that's got to suck for
you and so I want to know how we're
going to fix it. So, I'm going to be
very vulnerable with how I am rather
than making about them. So, this is
again back to the self-reliance piece.
Uh, entrepreneurs who are self-reliant
have a hard time expressing when they're
hurt. [snorts] Have a hard time
expressing some sort of this isn't
working for me really well. And
therefore, the problem is always about
the other person instead of about them
helping fix you fix your issue, which is
the way an organization is designed,
right? the energy is backwards if you're
trying to like fix everybody's issues
rather than everybody's fixing your
issues. Like if I was to invest in your
company as an example
and I got to pick one person who was
just stoked as hell, I would pick the
CEO
because that's going to be the best
investment. If the CEO is happy with the
way the company's going, the company is
going the way it should be going. If the
head of marketing is happy, but the CEO
is miserable about where the company's
going, that's not a good investment.
So, the happiness of the CEO is where
everybody needs to be pointed. It
doesn't mean that the CEO's job isn't to
be helpful to people, but it means that
the general energy of the company is
supposed to be towards pleasing the CEO,
making the CEO happy, which self-reliant
CEOs have a really hard time like
getting through their head because that
puts them in the position of the
authority that they don't particularly
want to be because authority was bad in
their childhood. So, so that's an
example. So, so those are all ways that
I would talk to somebody if I'm having
that hard conversation. So, there are
like very practical skills of having
hard conversations. But the biggest
skill on all over all of this stuff is
the internal space. If you feel like
you're bad for having the conversation,
if you feel like this is completely
reasonable for me to ask, if you feel
like I'm actually helping this person
become more empowered and and I'm doing
them a service and helping them become a
better at their job,
like that state of mind has a huge
impact on how the person receives it. So
I'll just give you like a very short
example. If I was like, "Hey, Sean,
you're such a dick."
Like, "Why are you such a dick?"
Or if I said,
"Oh, Sean, you're being a dick."
You're going to take those two things
very, very differently
because in one case, I don't want you to
be a dick and in the other case, I'm
like, "Oh, you know, you're being a
dick. That's okay." And so your attitude
coming in, if you're scared, you're like
more likely to get attacked. You're more
likely to have a bad experience with it.
So your your
calm,
your what I would call veagal authority,
your nervous system authority coming
into the room and your understanding of
you're here to be of service to this
person is going to make all the
difference.
>> You have um this cool quote. I think it
I don't have in front of me. I think it
was something like negative self-talk is
always wrong or something like that
which like I read that and I was that
was kind of shocking to me and it seems
like self-t talk is a really important
thing and a lot of like ambitious people
I think are like they're like their
biggest hater
>> most people generally
are do you have any um patterns that you
have seen of self-t talk and what are
the practical tips on improving that? So
there's there's like three or four
different kind of self-t talk abuse
cycles that you you're like there's like
the really overt one which is like
you're up why are you up why didn't you
like why don't you do this why didn't
you do that there's that version there's
then there's the version of you got to
do this now you got to do this you got
to do this why don't you do this you got
to do this don't forget to do this you
got to do this there's another version
of negative selft talk then there's like
some like
kind of hidden ones which are like uh
Uh, you've got it. You can do this. It's
all good. You've got this thing. You can
do this thing. Which you would like,
could you imagine going to, you know,
Michael Jordan and going, "Yeah, you can
do it. You can you can shoot the basket.
I know you can, Mike." Like, you would
never do it because you have confidence
in that person. So, this this subtle
undermining saying that you actually
need this, right? It's not you're fine
either way. And like there's not like a
natural confidence in it. So that's all
there's about 20 tools to work with
selft talk negative selft talk one of
the ways that you know it's negative
selft talk is cuz it's repeating right
so when when negative selft talk starts
dying in your system when it starts a
atrophying
you just have a lot less thought just is
a lot less thought occurs and the
thought that you have is more like
epiphies it's like oh here's a cool idea
oh that's a cool idea they're not
repetitive ative over and over again
thoughts. So I'll give you just a couple
really practical ones.
Um if you try to change the selft talk
it's very inefficient. If you change the
way you react to the selft talk it's far
far more efficient. Your selft talk is
like, "Wow, you just really screwed up
that podcast, Joe."
And like most people, they listen to
that the way that they would listen to a
think about the politician you hate most
talking on stage. And then think about
the person in the audience who's like,
"Yep. Uh-huh. Yeah. Yeah. That's right.
Uh-huh. Yeah." That's how we listen to
our selft talk. Most of us listen to our
selft talk as, you know, oh, you screwed
that up. It's like, "Yep, I screwed that
up. I should do something about that."
Like, that's that's the relationship.
So, instead, you change the reaction to
it. Like, "Oh, you screwed that stuff
up. Oh, I see how scared you are. I see.
I'm right here with you. You can be
scared." Or, "You up. Uh, wow. That's
really shitty management. Could you try
to manage me in a different way,
please?" You up. Prove it.
You up. Well, really? I think you up. So
you're changing the reaction. And so
like a great experiment to run on this
is think about the reaction that you
want to experiment with. It doesn't have
to be good or bad. It's just an
experiment. And you every time your
negative selft talk happens that day,
every time you remember you react in
this way that you're experimenting with.
And then 2 days later you do a new
experiment. 2 days later you do a new
experiment. So you're constantly
changing the way that you're reacting to
your selft talk. And just like both of
you are different when you're
interacting with each other than when
you're interacting with your significant
other or your kids if you have them or
your best friend from college.
We the the voice in our head reacts
differently depending on how we treat it
and you get to start seeing that.
And so that's a really simple way to
start man not manage but start like
bringing awareness and therefore
changing and transforming your negative
selft talk. The other another really
good one that's just really easy is
like name like write out here are the 20
things the negative voice in my head
says the most and look for seven ways
they're not true and if you can't find
them ask your friends because what your
negative voice in your head is saying is
not true. I I can give you if you tell
me anything that your negative voice in
your head says to you on a regular basis
I can prove and I can tell you five ways
it's not true. Hey, can I ask you a
question that um it sort of violates
that rule, you know, never ask a man a
question that a salary depends on uh the
answer or whatever?
>> You can try. Yeah.
>> So, [laughter] so you know uh whenever I
learn about this stuff and as you can
see I got notes and notes right now like
I love I get like really fascinated by
this. You're saying words like veagal
authority. I'm like oh I got to go look
at that. I want to learn that. I want to
learn to do this. And then within like I
would say as soon as I pass like the
90minute mark of any of this I'm like
completely exhausted and I almost like
go through like this cycle where I start
out as a idiot caveman. Then I think I'm
becoming this like elevated higher level
being who's really in touch with
everything and then I'm like oh my god
this is so much work. I just want to go
back to being a a lovable idiot again at
the end of this. And like dude it's all
good. Don't worry about it. like you
know I go and and I think actually
recently this kind of a maxing
kind of phrase caught on at least in
Silicon Valley. Other people are
probably like what the hell's this guy
talking about? But um this idea of like
you know you're trying too hard to be
too smart. You're too in touch with your
emotions. You're over therapized like
there is a reaction to the reaction.
>> Yeah. And I almost wonder like are
people better off just being kind of
like more like a dog? Like just dumb and
happy, you know, just wagging our tail
and and running around and, you know,
licking our butts. Like are we just
happier that way than trying to go do
all this work and kind of master the the
psyche and all of its different parts?
>> Yeah, that's a great question. Um, you
have it seems like you have two
questions in there. the so let me
address the first one which is that
cycle that you get into which is oh I'm
super inspired and now I feel exhausted
and the the thing that's happening there
is that in your mind you're telling
yourself you have to do all this stuff
and that's what makes it exhausting
rather than like what's the one cool
experiment I'm going to run this week
>> and
and that's maybe yours
another person's is like I have to be
perfect and so that like takes all the
joy out of it and and and makes it like
less effective.
So to me
it's like how you approach it is
incredibly important both for the
effectiveness and for whether it's
worthwhile.
Um you know the way I think about
meditation is a is a is kind of an
example. One of the things that I say is
meditation for most people is just
self-abuse because they're just sitting
there trying to manage themselves for 90
minutes, right? And there's no enjoyment
in it. And so the question is like how
do you enjoy meditation?
That that's a question. Or how do you
enjoy self-rowth or self-awareness or
understanding yourself better instead of
making it a grind? If you can do that,
then it's great and it's totally worth
it. and it's lovely and you'll be
inspired to do it. But if it becomes
like this to-do list so that one day
you'll be good enough so that you know
if you make it like your company right
which is once I get enough money and I
have enough power then I'll be happy
once I you know understand myself enough
and I deal with the voice in my head and
blah blah blah blah blah then I'll be
happy and then I'll be done or you can
be like oh like what can I learn today?
What's the what's the experiment I can
run
>> right? And this is the same way that I
would suggest if you want to learn how
to market. It's the same thing like
what's the experiment you can run? What
can you learn today? What can you read
about that's fun to read about? What's
the cool thing to try? Rather than oh my
god, I got to do this because my
business completely depends on it.
>> Right?
>> You're going to make a lot more progress
on the first than the second.
>> I think that's a great insight. I want
to come back to the second question, but
just to add on to that, last year I
decided to learn the piano and I had two
teachers. The first teacher I went to
made me almost quit the first day
because we sat down and they were like,
"All right, so here's what you're going
to need to learn. Uh, here's the musical
notation. We're going to memorize all
these letters and here's what we're
going to learn rhythm and we're going to
learn the scales, but you can't get the
scales if you don't first don't have
finger control and posture. Why are you
sitting like that?" And but like she
basically presented the whole elephant
that I'm going to have to eat. And I was
like, "Oh god, I'm like I'm just tired
thinking about what all I'm going to
have to do just to be able to this
stupid dream of mine. how much did I
really want this anyways? And then the
second teacher, so I [clears throat]
luckily I didn't quit. I just I bumped
into a second teacher and then the
second teacher was like, "Cool. So like
what what made you want to do this?
What's a song you like and what would be
cool if you could play it?" I'm like,
"Ah, this song." She's like, "Oh, you
know what? That's actually not that
hard. Here, forget the left hand. We're
just going to do the right hand and
we're just going to learn this intro
lick. You'll walk out of here. You'll be
able to play this little thing, right?"
>> And you know, it just got c. And then
it's like, "Oh, do you want to be able
to play the next thing? You're going to
have to learn what a chord is. You know
what a chord is?" And then I learned the
next thing progressively and now I can
play the piano. Right. It's like that
for all things in life. Uh so what you
said definitely re I didn't realize the
connection between those two until you
said that.
>> Yeah. If anybody told us what we had to
do to make our business successful and
like just handed like this is everything
you're going to have to do. Like most
people would be like that.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Or having kids or anything
else like that. Uh can we can we do the
second part now of uh are we better off
just being uh sort of you know
boxing and and not over introspecting
not overly getting in touch with our
feelings and just saying like feel good
do more doesn't feel good do less let me
just move on and not overthink it it can
potentially work out if you're super
lucky and the world doesn't change under
your feet but it's not going to work out
otherwise
meaning like the CEO of a tech company
that has
really really hard recruitment because
everybody because AI everybody with any
kind of AI degree is already recruited
is going to have to have a different set
of skills and understanding than the
person who's running a tomato 50,000
acre tomato farm and potentially the CEO
of one is not going to be successful and
the CEO of the other even though they
might be great CEOs in the business of
their choice because one is not high
margin, one is low margin, one is about
a certain kind of efficiency, one is a
certain kind of creativity. So if you
are not self-aware, then you better have
landed in a place where you by nature
are are going to be capable. And that
place can't change. But if you are going
to be required to change as a human
being and change who you are and your
identity as a human being to maintain or
continue success,
then you're just shooting yourself in
the foot by not being self-aware.
There's also this kind of trajectory of
self-awareness. Like the beginning is
why am I doing this work and then I
can't see the change? Other people are
telling me I'm changing but I can't see
the change. Why am I even doing this?
And then there's like holy this is
life is better. And then when you hit
the holy life is better moment
often times like two or three years for
people that they really get that moment
then it's just like why in the hell
would I ever stop this?
>> You know it's a little bit like working
out. I speaking of like working out and
actually Sean's example with the piano
was awesome and we've only been talking
for an hour and I'm like totally bought
in. I love what you do. I believe what
you were saying is true. But in the back
of my head I'm like this sounds amazing.
I'm a little overwhelmed. I don't know
where to start. And if it's like working
out and if you said you know the end
goal is you want to bench 300 lb over
the next year. like here's like a really
interesting progression and here's like
uh some experiments or workouts you can
do each week. It might be too reductive,
but are there like a this idea of
experimenting weekly is pretty cool.
That sounds exciting and that sounds
fun. Is there like a checklist or a
playbook where it's like
>> No, I think starting point is a good
word. Like if somebody listened to this
great what, you know, what's a beautiful
place in the next 24 hours, 48 hours
that they could go that what's a thing
they could do that would this get get
them on the road? Yeah. And like what
are and then what's the progression and
where are some other weekly experiments
that I could like follow to improve
myself?
>> Yeah. So there's I can tell you how I
did and I can tell you the resources
that we have for people. So I just
basically pick topics that
I was interested in. I would read
something on that topic and I would
design an experiment for myself and I'd
run that experiment for a week. And I
actually have a book that I just
finished writing that'll be published in
like whatever a year and something that
has 52 experiments on different topics.
Um and and then a whole bunch of writing
on these topics.
>> What's one of them?
>> A really cool s super cool experiment is
so right now
enjoy yourself. Don't change what you're
doing at all
and but just enjoy what you're doing 10%
more. Right. Totally possible, totally
capable. No, nothing to it. So, just do
that five times a day for the next week.
>> Five times a day. Go, oh, how do I enjoy
myself without changing anything? Just
5% more, 10% more.
>> That sounds like so basic and almost
stupid. And then I think of myself
wanting to do that and I'm like, that's
actually really helpful.
>> Like [laughter] super. Yeah. It's like
all of a sudden like you'll be sitting
in a meeting and you'll like your whole
mindset will change and then the thing
you say will change. And yeah, that's a
simple like really cool little
experiment to run. The other one is I
think we talked about the one with the
voice in the head. That's another great
experiment to run. Another great
experiment to run would be um Oh yeah,
this one's good. Especially if you're a
grinder. Don't do anything you don't
enjoy for a week. Do go to work and you
can only do the that you enjoy. And
at some point in that week, there's
going to be something that happens. And
I'll tell you my experience of this. I
did this before I had a business. And I
was sitting in front of the trash.
And I hated taking the trash out. But I
also didn't enjoy smelling the trash. So
I was sitting there like,
but what do I do? Cuz I've committed to
not doing anything I don't enjoy. And
then I was like, oh, I have to figure
out how to enjoy taking out the trash.
And so that's another cool experiment is
just see what it's like to live a week
doing only what you enjoy because a lot
of the lack of enjoyment that occurs is
because we tell ourselves we have to
endure it when we absolutely could be
enjoying it.
>> So you said you said something in that
first experiment. You said without doing
anything different enjoy it more. Which
to me reads like and you know because
one version of how do I take out the
trash more? Oh, I'm going to listen to
my favorite song while I do it. Okay, I
changed what I was doing, right? That's
that's fair.
>> But there's the other version which is
I'm literally not going to do anything
different. I'm just going to feel it
more. I'm going to like bring my
awareness.
>> That's why they're that's why they're
two experiences, two experiments, right?
>> And I I had this when we sold a company
and then I asked my business partner
Ben. I was like, dude, how does it feel
big, you know, big win for you? Like,
you know, first like how does it feel?
Is it is it what you thought? He's like,
honestly, no, not at all. He's like, I
don't feel anything. Yeah.
>> And we were laughing and he didn't know
what to make of it. So his meaning he
put on that was like dude was I chasing
the wrong goal this whole time? Like am
I was I wrong in what I wanted? And what
I kind of reframed or what I my life
experience was this. I was like dude I
think all these feelings are like a
muscle. You just never how many times
before this did you feel ecstatic and
triumphant and never. So what' you think
you just start today and suddenly feel
it at level 100? Like you never used
that muscle before. So like the actual
thing to do was practice using that
muscle when without having to sell your
company and then you know you sort of
build up the capacity to feel but you
can't just like I think we we think oh
my happy is your happy dude I got an
uncle who I'm like his capacity to feel
happy is just fundamentally higher like
a V2 max. It's way higher than mine. Is
that does that line up with like I've
never done the research. This is my life
experience. Yes, definitely. Definitely.
Especially the positive emotions, but
they're the scariest emotions for most
people to feel because they're the
biggest identity destroying emotions.
They just wreck your identity.
>> The positive ones are.
>> The positive ones. Yeah.
>> Why? Why does that destroy your
identity?
>> Go be in bliss and find out where you
are.
>> Well, I I I experienced that when I had
kids. When I had kids, I I I wrote a
post about this. I was like, not having
kids was so much better in terms of
ambition because it's quite simple. Uh,
I just work, work, work, and there's a
clear ladder and you just climb it. And
then you have kids and you're like, I
only mostly care about this and
everything else is insignificant.
>> Yeah.
>> And you're like, that part of me just
died. I I guess you grieve it a little
bit. I don't know how you feel, but like
when you have children, you're like,
everything that I thought I cared about,
I now care about significantly less.
>> Less. Yeah. And it like and I'm happy. I
prefer this life.
>> And yet you're still working and still
being effective, which is also an
interesting thing to let your mind
recognize that the identity doesn't have
to be so attached to be able to be
successful.
Yeah. One more experiment that I think
is really cool for entrepreneurs,
especially if they have cuz we've been
talking about self-reliance.
Thank people a day. Consciously
look around and go, "What did somebody
do for me that I'm grateful for?" and
thank five people a day. It'll totally
change your self-reliance pattern.
>> Hey, how do you find joy and how do you
find what you should be doing? Because
you're like find one of your exercises
was do only what you like or you know
like or enjoy something more. But that's
actually kind of complicated because I
don't think a lot of people have
actually asked themselves or can't
answer what do I love doing?
>> Yeah. I think because it's a false I
think that's really just like a self-
abuse in disguise, right? Like what's my
purpose? What's my purpose is just a way
to beat yourself up that you don't have
your purpose. What do I enjoy? I think
that the people that I
find who have purpose and and enjoy what
they do, they a lot of them weren't like
I think that what I'm going to do is I'm
going to like really get into risk
analysis,
but they ended up there, but they
learned how to geek out on it and enjoy
the thing itself. So, I think the way
that you find what you enjoy is on a
day-to-day basis asking yourself, how
would I enjoy doing this? How do I enjoy
this? What would make it a little bit
better? How would I change this? And and
I think for entrepreneurs, they think
that that's a nice to have, but it's
it's far more important than that. So,
if I had an a car, if I wanted an
efficient company, we think of it as a
fast company. I got from A to B quickly.
But if we had a car, A to B quickly
isn't an efficient car. That's just a
fast car. An efficient car is a car that
gets to A to B without a lot of energy.
And so if you want efficiency in your
life,
it's how much energy you spent in that
day.
And often that does end up making you go
faster. And so if I get to the end of
the day and I say, "How much did I enjoy
myself?" That's the best measure of
efficiency
because I have energy for the next day
and I want to come back. If I do a yoga
class and I enjoyed the hell out of it,
I'm far more likely to come back and do
yoga and do it well tomorrow than if I
had a yoga class that sucked and I hated
it.
And so as people learn that like how
enjoyment works in their system, how to
enjoy what they enjoy, what they're
great at,
then their whole business becomes far
more efficient. And as a matter of fact,
we get a lot of people who come and say,
"I'd like to work for you." And I'll
just say, "What's your passion? What's
the thing that you care about that you
would love doing?" And if they say the
thing that we have a slot for, then
we'll talk to them
because it's so like if someone's
naturally motivated, it's so useful.
It's interesting you say that. You know,
I when when Sam asked these questions
kind of like, "How do you know?" You
know, my guess was that you were going
to just be like, you know, when you see
it, you feel it. It's not a It's not a
heady thing. You can't think your way
into this or out of this or, you know,
to analyze your way into success in
these like there's a whole like kind of
east west or two two sides of the brain
type of thing. Yeah. But I feel like
when you're answering some of these, you
you are kind of thinking your way
through, I guess. Can you talk about
just noticing or feel rather than where
does that play in for you?
>> I can give you a great story on this. So
my wife and I were sitting we we do
these very intense long retreats and so
it's very tiring and we were at the end
of one of the retreats and there was
this investment we could have made that
would have given us enough money where
we didn't have to start a business. And
we were sitting there thinking and and
um I said I'm really glad that didn't
happen because we wouldn't have done
this. And she said, "Yeah, me too." And
I said, "I'm just curious. Would you
would you sell this business for a
billion dollars if we could not do it
again? Like we would be done doing it,
but we'd get a billion dollars." And
both of us went like this. We both went,
"We wouldn't." Like that was our that
was our answer. And I don't know. I told
my I came home told the story to my
daughters and then like two or three
months later one of my daughters comes
in and says
I found my billion dollar idea. I'm like
cool
something you can grow into a billion
dollars. And she's like no something I
wouldn't sell for a billion dollars.
>> That's cool.
>> And so if you're doing something that's
like deeply meaningful to you, that's
one way to test if that's something
that's deeply meaningful to you. If
you're doing it for other reasons, if
you're doing it because you think it's
going to make you happy, if you're doing
it because you think people will like
you or because you'll have enough money
or to just be better or to win or
something like that, those are those can
actually create very big and successful
businesses, but they won't create
contentment. I like uh talking with
people like you because you have this
really cool perspective where you've
talked to the titans of industry, the
best of the best, the Illuminati, you
know, you like you have seen them
>> and we all know what they appear like in
the media or on podcasts like this where
they usually look like they have their
act together or they'll show just a
little bit of vulnerability to show that
like they're one of us. But are there
any interesting stories or observations
about the 1% the 1% of performers that
would surprise us or at least entertain
us on how these guys might think that
might surprise us or be different?
>> Yeah. Specifically, I can't do
obviously, but um what I could say is
that the there's nothing I've said on
this podcast that I haven't said to one
of the titans of industry.
Like there's there's that the the things
that you're wrestling with are the exact
same things that they're wrestling with,
right? The
>> what what attributes do you tend to
notice? Are they 10 out of 10 on and or
one out of 10 on?
>> The really really the exceptional ones
of like very fastpaced businesses. So
not like if you can be a slow paced
business then there's a different kind
of attitude. You can be you can actually
be quite self-abusive in a slow fa paced
business, but in a fast-paced business,
you can't seconduess yourself very much.
So very very few of them are
secondguessers.
>> So they just are like and part of it is
because they have to make so many
decisions in a day. And and so
decisiveness is another one especially
for the fast-paced industries. There are
some um like investment. If you're an
investor and you can be a billionaire
investor, you can really second guess
yourself a ton and still be a successful
investor. But if you're the CEO of a of
a tech company, you that's in fast pace,
you can't do that. The other thing that
I think those very high performers, it's
not all of them, but I would I would say
like at least 60 maybe 70%,
they both feel like they're better than
everybody and worse than everybody
simultaneously.
So they on one level
in their conscious mind they're like I
am more capable than people than the
average person but underneath they're
like I'm broken and so they're kind of
doing this thing because they know that
they're better and they're trying to
prove that they're not broken.
It's not all the time but it's it's more
common in that population than in any
other population that I've seen. There's
a lot of people walk around thinking
that they're better than everybody,
right? I mean, you can you can go down
into like the drags of our society and
you will find somebody who thinks
they're better than everybody, but that
like underlying like, oh, I'm broken
simultaneously with it and the way that
that presents is very it's there's a lot
of it in that realm. You know, one of
the things we did in this podcast that's
sort of backwards probably from most
podcasts. Most podcasts start with like,
"Tell me about your background and your
story."
>> Yeah.
>> And we do it the opposite. We say, "Show
me all the gold you've collected on your
journey." First, we start there. And
then we say, "Where'd you get all this,
man? Where did you what kind of journey
did you go on?
>> Can you give us now, now that we've, you
know, gotten to see some of the gold,
can you give us a little bit of the the
the journey?" And I'm curious about one
thing in particular, but I read
something about like an an 8-second
meditation experience. I'm very curious
about that, but if you give us the
journey, but make sure you hit that
along the way.
>> Okay.
>> Uh, yeah. I mean, I grew up going all
over the world. I think by the time I
was 28, I lived in 26 places.
>> My dad was a CEO, but also um became an
alcoholic. And so I would rebelled
against that. had a mohawk, was a
skateboarder, got kicked out of my first
college, graduated valadictorian from my
second college, and then first thing I
did when I left college was like, I'm
just having adventures one after the
other. So, I butchered fish in Alaska
and I hitchhiked um throughout the
United States and then I did
international stock lending and I was in
a band and I so I was just like I'm
having whatever adventure I want from
like
>> with James Bond man
>> because well it's cuz my I saw my dad
just like do this corporate thing and
end up in misery. I was like yeah I'm
not doing that. Then I met my wife and
my wife was like, "If we're we're going
to get married, we're going to see a
therapist, we're going to do a 10-day
silent retreat, and we're going to
travel through um third world together
for like 6 months. And if we can do
those three things, we're going to be
capable of getting married and being
successful." So those were her tasks.
And so I did them. The therapy was
amazing. Uh we got blessed with a really
good therapist and they're pretty rare.
And then the silent retreat was my first
time meditating ever. And on day three
of aa they have you know it's when it
changes from putting all your attention
into your breath to like moving your
attention through your body. And I had
this experience of like evaporation
samadei is what some people would call
it. this experience of I am one with
everything and everything is good and it
lasted eight seconds and then
[clears throat] it was like getting
hooked on heroin. I my entire life
changed. I was like whatever the that is
I'm obsessed. And unfortunately I went I
went about it in a very inefficient way.
I very much was like once I get there
I'll be happy. It was just the search
for enlightenment was just like porn for
perfectionism. It was just like my porn,
right? And but the the plus side was
that like I just because I had authority
issues, I just went and explored
everything and took nothing very
seriously and made everything an
experiment. So instead and then now
that's how we teach like when we do our
courses, everything is done as an
experiment. It's not like we're talking
and saying this is how things are. We're
like go and experience the ship for
yourself. Here's how you do it. You can
do it with people right now. It's very
in the- moment experimentation.
And I wasn't willing to say, you're the
authority. You're the guru. I was like,
I'm going to listen to every single
modality that I can find from
neuroscience to psychology to, you know,
traditions that are 2,000 years old. I'm
going to try 10 forms of meditation. I'm
going to do the Hoffman process. I'm
going to do sematic work. I'm I just did
everything. And I was pretty dedicated
to that. I'm not pretty. I was like
totally dedicated. I didn't work for
seven years. I like lived off credit
cards. I meditated for like 7 hours a
day looking searching and um I was I was
obsessed with it. The search ended the
what what people would call awakening
happened and it wasn't an end at all.
There was no finish line just like you
know selling a company. It was just like
oh I see how this whole thing is just
easier and and more spacious than I
thought it was.
And then my identity got trapped in that
for a while like I was the awake guy and
then that evaporated.
And in that time period we had kids and
then the kids were where the big
emotional work came in was like really
learning. I there was this thing called
handin-hand parenting which I highly
recommend a book called listen which is
like one of the most profound practices
in my life and that was really where the
big emotional understanding started
coming in that that like oh I can be
with my children in these big emotions
and all they need to do is feel them and
accept them to like become amazing kids
and now my girls are you know 17 and 20
and they are freaking amazing and it is
I think all because of handin and and my
wife, she's amazing. And um so that was
it. And then some point I became a
venture capitalist and uh
>> as one does.
>> As one does. Yeah. I uh [snorts] I
literally went from meditation, I did
art, and then became a venture
capitalist. I
>> you you're like a sellout.
>> Well, both of them just sit around all
day doing that a lot. [laughter]
No, what happened was uh I was doing
this large scale art installation for a
wealthy family and I was giving them
business advice cuz before I had done
international stock lending and other
things and I it was like at the time
when oil was going through the roof and
gold was going through the roof and I
was just telling them like hey here's
this thing and they did and they made a
lot of money. That's that's like a
hilarious thought by the way. a guy
doing an arts installation at a rich
person's house. Got like the guru energy
and it's like, "Hey, uh, do you guys
want to discuss your bond portfolio?"
>> Yeah. Wait, what did you actually tell
them? What was going on? What was the
call?
>> Buy oil and gold. This is a long time
ago, right? But, um, I was like I've
always been obsessed with business as
well. So, and the way I think about
those years is I was meditating and
worrying about money. Those are the two
things I did. So, I had like a stack of
financial times in the corner. And so I,
you know, I was when they still had
papers and I would read the Financial
Times and because I started I one of the
jobs I did was international stock
lending and I I got like promoted three
times and so I was inside of like a
16-month period and so it was just kind
of it was just something that I always
thought about. And like one day we were
sitting having lunch and I was just
like, "Hey, here's this thing." So he
comes to me and he goes, "Hey,
do you want to come and work for us and
like help us in the family office?" And
I was like, "No, I'm I love being an
artist. It's good." And he says, "Well,
if you could do anything you want, just
tell us what it would be." And so 3
months later, I was like, "Well, I think
the biggest change agent on the planet,
this is around 2006." I was like, "It's
going to be clean techch. I think that
this is like the the biggest
technological changes on the planet, I
think, have come from from venture." So
I'd do that and then I would work in the
nonprofit like helping increase
consciousness particularly in children
and so he said yeah let's do it and it
turned out I was not a great investor
[laughter]
because I needed to be needed too much
like like a great investor is the
investor who's like they do I am
investing because you don't need me at
all and I was like I need to be needed
which was horrible as venture investor
and in that so the only way for me to be
successful was to coach the CEOs into
like turning their companies around. Uh
and we had a positive result on the
portfolio. So we invested more. So I was
investing for about 12 years. But pretty
soon the word about my coaching got out.
And in doing venture, the thing that I
realized about the personal work was
that if you take a standard business
tool and you put the awareness of
personal work into it, the standard
business tool gets better. Right? If we
have something that we teach called
view, it's in our connection course.
It's about how to communicate with
people, how to have hard conversations,
how to have sales conversations.
when people have it, they sell better,
they do product better, they talk to
their husbands and wives better, um they
have hard conversations better, and it's
because they're all related. And so, as
I was coaching people and learning all
these business tools as a VC and
blending them together, I just found
more and more effective ways to do it,
which made me a better coach. And so, at
some point, I was like, I should be
doing this and only this. And so 2016
>> 16 I started the transition. 2018 I
stopped working for the family and I
started building Art of Accomplishment
and we've been growing ever since.
>> You're fun to talk to because you this
stuff is all really helpful. Like I'm so
convinced now like you've got me
drinking the Kool-Aid where I'm like
here you talk about this and I'm like
nothing else matters except for this and
that's a little bit of an overwhelming
feeling. Is there like a practical way
that I can get started other than going
through one of your programs? Like
anything that you suggest I read or do
because this sounds very fascinating and
I'm like,
>> "Yeah,
>> I'm in."
>> Yeah. So, the one thing I would do, we
have a podcast that I think has now like
180 episodes and they're all on
different topics and it's all basically
some version of a teaching. So, I would
pick a topic that's like particular for
you. You're like, "Oh, wow. I'm a
perfectionist." So go to the
perfectionist podcast. I have
self-reliance issues. Go to the
self-reliance podcast
and then if there's not an experiment in
it, a lot of them have experiments that
you can run. Then design an experiment
from that and play there. We also have
an experiments page where it teaches you
how to design the experiments and how to
run them. That's another thing that I
think is really good. We have a podcast
on running and designing experiments.
That's another one. By the way, Sam so
brilliant that they call them exper he
frames everything as experiments because
so much of this industry that he's in is
a you should do this, you need to do
this, this is the way versus less
preachy, less rigid, more
>> like try this weird thing and see what
happens. You might be surprised.
>> Yeah, it's and it makes it more fun.
Yeah,
>> makes more fun. It's also there's
another reason for it. So if so we have
a part of our brain I'm not going to be
very specific about this but we have a
part of the brain called the habenula.
It's with all invertebras and it's
basically the part of our brain that
like traffics our dopamine and stuff
like that and it prevents us from making
the same mistake over and over and over
and over again. And the reason this is
is because if you're a bear and you're
fighting for sexual dominance and you
lose it be really stupid to go and like
fight the next day, right? If you eat
the mushroom it makes you sick. It'd be
really stupid to eat that mushroom the
next day. Unfortunately, what this does
for us is it means like we're not going
to make the second sales call because we
just got rejected or when we stop, we
eat that piece of chocolate cake that we
talked about earlier, I'm going to just
quit my diet. That's what it does in our
brain. So, if you frame it as an
experiment, then what you're doing is
you're constantly learning and you're
never failing. And so they did this
study about people who were like I think
it was at or below poverty and they
figured out who lost weight
when they tried. And the people who did
were the people who were constantly
iterating where there was no we fail.
There's just I'm going to try this now.
I'm going to try this. Now we're going
to try this. Which we obviously see in
business, right? Those are the people
who succeed in business. They keep on
trying new stuff until they find the
thing that works. And so to see
self-awareness and as a series of
experiments and every experiment you
learn and all you need to do is learn
about yourself
then you never really can fail and it
works a lot better. And if you think
about like fixing a watch if you
understand a watch you can fix it. If
you understand yourself right you can
change.
>> You're like uh the worst doctor is a
dermatologist because when they go out
to parties with their family everyone's
like I got a rash. Check this out. uh
what [laughter] is this? And like people
are like popping their tops at parties
like what do you think this is? And uh
like if you go to a party with you,
everyone's like, "Fix me." Uh or like
give me the answer. It must be
exhausting. You You probably have to lie
about what you do.
>> It's a little Yeah. It can be annoying.
I Chris Williamson. Do you have you do
you all know Chris?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. So Chris Williamson was um hanging
out with me and he was uh he was like,
"You know, my life is walking down the
street, some you know UPS driver says,
"Hey man, good podcast." I'm like,
"Thanks." Your life is, "Hey man, I've
got daddy issues. Can we have a quick
session?" [laughter]
Yeah.
So I would say that's one good way to
start. The other good way to start is on
YouTube. I do these 15inute coaching
sessions. I do some with business folks,
some without business folks. They're
incredibly powerful. They're incredibly
potent. And so, if you can go through
them and say, "Oh, I have this issue."
And then watch the coaching session, you
can get change that's not just on an
intellectual level. This has been a
treat because I'm I'm seeking uh I'm
looking to hire an executive coach. Sean
has one and he's we're both like in some
transitionary periods of our lives with
families and like business and so this
was like a treat for us because I think
I needed this uh I needed this. This was
the perfect medicine.
>> Cool. I'm happy to make some
recommendations for you if you're
interested.
>> I'm all yours. Yeah, tell me everything.
You can tell me you can tell me off air.
Yeah.
>> Okay,
>> brother. You got me eaten out of your
hand right now. I'll do whatever you
say. [laughter]
the that as far as the book, the one
thing that I think would be really
useful, we have a program that's
specifically for
venture-back startups that have found
product market fit but are under 50
people and we have a program for their
executive teams. So, their executive
teams come and do a summit with us twice
a year. Super effective. Basically, we
are all about getting that how do we
have the hard conversations quickly and
effectively and creating that so that
you know you know and I know that like
two founders not getting along can cost
a business decades if not the entire
business and hundreds of thousands of
dollars and so we find the working with
the the team the executive team is far
more efficient for having a change both
with the CEO inside the company so that
would be it's called the council
And we open up applications once a year.
>> Dude, it's crazy the responsibility you
have. Like uh I read that the OpenAI
team sends a car, picks you up and you
you like coach the whole team or you
coach the execs and then I'm on Twitter
and they're like uh hey I lead safety
research. It's like like the big story
right now is like anthropics guys like
hey like we think there's a greater than
10% chance that AI kills all of
humanity. You know what I mean? Like
it's like first of all they need a
little comms coaching. I don't know if
you do that on the side, but that would
be nice. [laughter]
But secondly, like you know what
responsibility? Like coaching the people
that are building the thing, the bomb,
you know, like either the
[clears throat] greatest thing ever, the
worst thing ever. Sometimes they say
it's the greatest ever and sometimes
they tell us it's going to be the worst
thing ever. It's got to be a pretty uh
pretty heavy thing.
>> Yeah, that's that's really interesting.
So just to be very clear about my like I
I coach people at OpenAI. I don't co
coach the whole leadership team and I've
coached most of the people who are in
the research like leading the research
department and I've worked with people
in our like inerson and other programs
from all the AI labs. They all come one
multiple from all of them have come
through our thing. I have a really
interesting take on this.
You know, if you you've had a kid, your
wife's in the O or in the birthing room
or maybe she you had a duel at the
house, but just imagine like she's
giving birth to this thing and now
imagine like there's protests outside
and there's people saying that they're
going to destroy humanity and
you know like these people are doing
something that's like substantial and as
a society we are really not being
supportive. And the reason I say being
supportive is because the outcome is
going to be different, right? Like I'm
sure they're out there, but I haven't
met one of them yet who's trying to
not do something that's good for
humanity that they don't and they're not
concerned. You you must have seen the
the tweet Sean's referring to that
actually this isn't in your in your
wheelhouse maybe of expertise, but it
might be given that you talked to all
these cool people. Do you actually have
an opinion on what that basically for
the listener the the tweet was a guy who
worked at Claude quit and he said the
there's a 10% chance or more that
everyone's going to die because of AI.
It was a very uh
>> one guy quit and then the guy who's
still there who leads that team that
that guy was on said no he's right. We
do believe that. I personally think it's
a greater than 10% chance.
>> Yeah.
>> Um
>> do you have an opinion on um the
seriousness?
>> I do. I have a very very strong opinion.
I've sat with a whole bunch of
researchers and they were asked like
these are the people building it and
they were asked 20 questions.
Does AGI exist now? Will it ever exist?
Are the things and then they were asked
to line up on this line and they lined
up very very differently like they were
spread out. Okay, is it going to destroy
the world? Is it going to be the best
thing for humanity? They're all spread
out on the line. every single question.
There's not everybody on one corner and
everybody on the other corner. And so my
take away from that is they're re
they're thinking about what's going to
happen with AI has far more to do with
how they were raised than it has to do
with any kind of reality.
>> That's such a you answer. That's a and
it's a beautiful answer.
>> So that's that's that's my opinion on
it. I mean, of course, this has a chance
to destroy humanity. So does nuclear
weapons and so does global warming and
so does and something will eventually
you know and the the question that I ask
myself personally is like what can I do
that can
affect a positive outcome and am I
participating in that and somebody can
say that's easy Joe because you're you
know coaching people like Sam
but I would say it is a democracy of
clicks and and money that's going to
determine AI more than any one leader.
And I think we sherk our responsibility
by saying it's about one leader who's
going to do it.
>> Does that make you feel better, Sean, or
no?
>> I don't think so.
>> Honestly, no. [laughter] Not at all.
>> Some are going to die.
>> No, not even that. uh it's I guess on on
one level there's a sort of humor in the
situ to use your analogy of like you
they're sort of birthing this technology
and you said a lot of the opinions of
these people has less to do let me
paraphrase what you said a lot of their
opinions has less to do with the facts
on the ground of the research what
they're seeing in the data versus how
they were raised you know their daddy
issues and it's like AI's daddy has
daddy issues therefore maybe the AI is
gonna have daddy issues as it grows up
um you know
>> yeah just just like just like Meta's
business is a reflection of the
consciousness of Mark Zuckerberg.
>> Yeah, I think that's why you coach
because you can affect that. I think
that's why maybe you have comfort
because you know some of the people I
think that's why a lot of the people who
are just in the YouTube comments who
have sort of billionaire aversion, tech
guy aversion, right? This is like
>> this is like if you go look at the
sentiment the sentiment around
>> that's horrible
>> billionaires tech leaders and
specifically the billionaire AI tech
leaders it's awful. like there is zero
trust,
>> zero um belief in the uh that those are
our great kings and fearless leaders
that we want to get behind.
>> Yeah.
>> Part of that is because of their own
poor communication and presentation. Uh
you know, so it's not like they're
>> they're just hated because of who they
are, right? They they contributed to
some of that.
>> Yeah.
>> And some of it is people's their own
current life situation makes them hate,
you know, and and that's you know, it's
just this weird complicated thing that's
going on. But uh to answer your question
Sam of you know does it make me feel a
lot better? No, not necessarily.
>> I sort of think of it like I don't know
just a much higher level of uh like the
earth has been around for billions of
years. The odds that I will exist when
the demise is here is very very very
very low.
>> The funniest the funniest tweet was uh
when the Antaric guy was like yeah 10%
chance it kills all humans. And then
somebody quote tweeted it and said by
the way LeBron was 9% to go to the
Sixers this summer. [laughter]
Just put that perspective for me.
>> I I I actually took a lot of comfort
when I was I was reading about the Dead
Sea Scrolls and I found out that it was
in it the the scrolls were kept by a
cult who saw the end of the world
coming. And I was like, "Oh, the end of
the world was coming."
>> Wait, wait, explain this. I don't even
know what what is the Dead
>> Desi Scrolls are like the the ancient
biblical text.
>> Yeah, exactly. that were like in a cave
somewhere and they were kept by a cult
just post Jesus I think that was like
the end of the world is coming and we
have to prepare for it and then we had
Y2K I don't know if you all are old
enough but that was the end of the world
then we had like 2012 the Mayan prophecy
that was the end of the world
>> so like humans do have a thing about
like the end of the world is coming we
do we do like that
>> Joe thanks for coming on man uh
everybody go check out Art of
Accomplishment and the podcast and all
the good Yeah, thanks for having me.
Appreciate it.
>> All right, that's it. That's the pod.